<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <correspDesc>
           <!-- 
from:	Millie Nieves <millie_nieves@sil.org>
reply-to:	millie_nieves@sil.org
to:	Jack Bowers <iljackb@gmail.com>
date:	Fri, Jul 14, 2017 at 3:05 PM
subject:	A few more quick questions (when you have time)
           -->
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName></persName>
              <date></date>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="recieved">
              <persName></persName>
              <date></date>
           </correspAction>
           <correspContext>
              <note></note>
           </correspContext>
        </correspDesc>
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <p>
               Hi Mille,
               
               Thanks for the Alvarado documents!
               
               I have a few more questions for whenever you have time. 
               
               (1) ña or ñaa(?)
               
               Welcome to Mixtecoland!  You cannot speak Mixtec without include “ña” or its extensions in your conversations. “ña” means “lo que” (in Spanish).  Barbara Hollenbach coined this “ña” as initial pronoun (pronombre inicial).  What I havenꞌt discovered is if ñaa or ña is the same thing.  Some of my Mixtec coworkers write “ña” and sometimes “ñaa”.  Two of them tried to explain the “ñaa” but I didnꞌt understand.  Perhaps is the same thing.  Thatꞌs beyond my understanding.  Sometimes they are thinking something they want to say and start to say, "ñaa" or sometimes they say, " na ñaa".  They are not counscious when they do like that.   It li like Mmmm!
               
               Ña is a initial pronoun, a relative pronoun, a complementizer, you could call it a nexus, it could be a thematic pronoun as I describe it sometimes on discourse analysis..
               
               Since I wonꞌt write the whole explanation, I attached a paper written by Barbara Hollenbach on this regard.
               
               I often see this, early on I called it an "Attributive Copula" but I'm not sure how it works, or what it is really. Nope.
               
               I notice it seems to occur in sentences declaring something about someone but I think there are a few different terms or uses of  'ña' (one being as relativizer? 'that'?)  Yes.
               
               The example I'm looking at is: Are these subordinate sentences?  Question.  Is this a natural sentence or an elicited sentence. I donꞌt know how to say this in English, but in Spanish (literally)  is something like: “los que (son) parientes son María y Pablo”.  Probably in English would be something like: María and Pablo are the ones who are relatives.  Something like that.  It is very important to have complete sentences.
               ña ta'an kuu Maria tsi Pablo
               "Maria and Pablo are siblings"
               
               This looks like aposition which is common in Mixtec.  But I will need to see the whole sentence.  What does “kue” mean here?  Is this part of another sentence. 
               Probably is something like, “my pants, the blue ones”.  But I donꞌt know how to translate “kue”.  Who formed this sentence?  a native speaker of Mixtec?
               tsatu yu ra, ña nchaa kue
               "my pants are blue"
               “mis pantalones, los que son azules” ‑ ‑ ‑ ‑ ‑ ‑kue?
               
               > How would you describe this words' meaning and grammatical function?
               
               (2) The work for "fast", how do you spell it?
               I have it written "tsa'an" ¿This is fast?  but as is the common problem, it is pronounced somewhere in between that and "tsaan". Also, in the 3 times I have it recorded, the tone is different on every one.
               I donꞌt remember a word in Mixtec that means "fast".  Mixtec people use other words to denote "fastness" depending on the context, like "vichi" now, today or "michumi" ("michuni") right now.  Also the verbs, "sketa" to run and "kunu" to escape (running) denote a fast event.  In Magdalena Peñasco "kunu" means to run.
               
               This verb probably means go. I donꞌt know the context for the word you are asking.  Possibly is a motion verb. If this is the motion verb "tsaꞌan"  it means that a person is (habitually) moving from a deictic center to an unmarked place.
               
               There is another "tsaꞌan" which means "to smell bad".
               
               (3) 'ra'
               
               Recently we discussed 'ra' and its different uses, I wanted to see how you would classify and explain the function in the following examples:
               Jack, it is important to know if the sentences below are natural sentences, or if they have been translated, or elicited.  I know that you are analyzing the copula, but it is better to have natural texts to find explicit and implicit copulas.  “kue” is not a copula, but “kuu”.  “Kuu” can appear at the end of the sentence, and is not the default way.  It marks important information.  So if you have “kuu” instead “kue” at the end of the sentence, it makes sense to me.
               
               So far the only function I have seen when “ra” is present in a discourse, is to indicate that what follows is important for the speaker.
               maa kue ra, nania Herminia
               "our mothers name is Herminia"
               (both of) Our mothers, are named Herminia"
               
               Maria tsi Pablo ra skulero kue (to me this is wrong)
               "Maria and Pablo are teachers"
               (no 'ña' or 'kuu')
               If this is “kuu” this sentence would say something like: 
               “María y Pablo, maestros son.”
               
               tsatu yu ra ña nchaa kue
               "my pants are blue" Mis pantalones, los azules (los que (son) azules)
               This is not the meaning.
               (no 'kuu')
               
               My interpretation of this is that when the subjects are put in the fronted position, the 'ra' is put there to link them as the main arguments of the verb which is to directly follow. Is that correct?  If you want to call it a link I wonꞌt complain, but this is not a simple link.  Mixtec people can also use it at the end of a clause, but the purpose is the same; what follows is prominent, important for the speaker.  The particle is present in different environments, not only after subjects.  For example, "Cha vichi ra, kunkatsi yoo, lesu."  And now, I will eat you rabbit.
               
               Tatsa'vi ni nchu'a! Tatsaꞌvi nchuꞌa ni!
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
