<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mixtec Correspondence Record 20170714-01</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc><!-- 
           from:	Millie Nieves <millie_nieves@sil.org>
reply-to:	millie_nieves@sil.org
to:	Jack Bowers <iljackb@gmail.com>
date:	
subject:	Re: Advice on verbs
mailed-by:	sil.org
signed-by:	sil.org
           -->
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="MN">Mille Nieves</persName>
               <date>Fri, Jul 14, 2017 at 2:12 AM</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="recieved">
               <persName xml:id="JB">Jack Bower</persName>
               <date>Fri, Jul 14, 2017 at 2:12 AM</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <note/>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            On 7/13/2017 6:30 AM, Jack Bowers wrote:
            Hi Mille,
            
            Thanks for the information, literature and feedback you gave me last week.
            
            I am now getting to my verbs to annotate and I have a bit more to learn and so I'm a bit slowed up. Previously, I unfortunately haven't been as systematic with my collection of verb data as I should have..
            
            I know in Mixtepec there is the Incompletive, Completive and Potential forms of the verbs, but I'm not quite sure how to classify the basic forms that they give you when you ask for the default verb, it seems they are often the same as the imperative form..
            e.g. 
            
            (when asking for general 'gloss' form of verb):
            '<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e39" xml:lang="en">to sing</span>
            </spanGrp>' &gt; 
            <seg xml:id="d1e38" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e39">kana</w>
            </seg> <note>This kana is the potential form without kun‑</note>
            
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="mood" target="#d1f40" ana="#CMND">imperative</span></spanGrp> form of verb:
            '<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1f40" xml:lang="en">sing!</span>
            </spanGrp>' &gt;
            <seg xml:id="d1f38" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1f40">kana</w></seg>
            <note ana="#TONE">I donꞌt remember the right tone for the imperative, but it is different from to sing.</note>
            
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e51" ana="#INCMPL">incompletive</span> <span>(3pl.inf)</span></spanGrp>:
            '<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e50" xml:lang="en">they are singing</span>
            </spanGrp>' &gt;
            <seg xml:id="d1e50" xml:lang="mix" type="phrase">
               <w xml:id="d1e51">tsita</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e53">kueyi</w>
            </seg>
            
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e62" ana="#CMPL">completive:</span> <span>(3pl.inf)</span></spanGrp>:
            '<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e61" xml:lang="en">they sang</span>
            </spanGrp>' &gt; 
            <seg xml:id="d1e61" xml:lang="mix" type="phrase">
               <w xml:id="d1e62">ntsíta</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e64">kueyi</w>
            </seg>  (?) (I don't  actually have this form)
            
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e72" ana="#POT">potential:</span> <span>(3pl.inf)</span></spanGrp>:
            '<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e71" xml:lang="en">they will sing</span>
            </spanGrp>' &gt;
            <seg xml:id="d1e71" xml:lang="mix" type="phrase">
               <w xml:id="d1e72">kunkana</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e74">kueyi</w>
            </seg>  (?) (I don't  actually have this form)
            
            A note on "
            <seg xml:id="d1e77" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e78">kana</w>
            </seg>".  As I know, kana means to sing when the rooster is singing or birds.  But the primary meaning is to call or to scream  (in some cases) depending on the context.  The conjugation would be: "
            <seg xml:id="d1e81" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e82">nikana</w>
            </seg>" (
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e82" ana="#CMPL">completive</span></spanGrp>); "
            <seg xml:id="d1e89" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e90">kana</w>
            </seg>" (
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e90" ana="#INCMPL">incompletive</span></spanGrp>); "
            <seg xml:id="d1e96" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e97">kunkana</w>
            </seg>" (
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="aspect" target="#d1e97" ana="#POT">potential</span></spanGrp>); "
            <seg xml:id="d1e103" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e104">kana</w>
            </seg>" (
            <spanGrp type="gram"><span type="mood" target="#d1e104" ana="#CMND">imperative</span></spanGrp>).  <note ana="#TONE">I donꞌt remember the tone for the imperative.  Perhaps MM.  Not all the imperatives have MM tone but I have observed that a group of imperatives have MM tone</note>.  See below the explanation for the other verb meaning "to sing".  
            
            <q who="#JB">&gt; What basic set of forms would you advise to collect when studying verbs?</q>  The basic form is the potential without the prefixes. When asking for verbs to a native speaker of Mixtec just use the infinitive form in Spanish to ask them and do the recording. Then you will get the basic form.  Varieties from the Highland Mixtec and  Lowland Mixtec are the same.  I mean, the basic form is the potential or future... 
            (e.g. forms and (if necessary person) that if you have them you can then infer the pattern for the rest of the forms)
            
            <q who="#JB">&gt;Is there one or more related varieties of Mixtec whose verb system is more closely akin to Mixtepec than others?</q>  I am not sure.  Perhaps eastern Juxtlahuaca.  But I donꞌt know any linguist studies those varieties.  But <lang>Mixtepec</lang> shares features from the Lowland Mixtec and Highland Mixtec as well.  Mixtec villages from the State of Guerrero are more or less related to Mixtepec.  Perhaps you can see <lang>Xochapa Mixtec</lang> and <lang>Alacatlatzala Mixtec</lang>.  I attached the popular grammar from A. Mixtec and a basic dictionary from <lang>Xochapa Mixtec</lang>.
            
            <q who="#JB">I do have most of the SIL Mixtec Syntax papers from 1989-1992? - The terminology is sometimes different in those papers, so it's kind of confusing in some cases where I'm not sure if they have different features (aspects) or they are just describing them differently (also it's frustrating because the files are just scans and you can't highlight or search the text)</q>
            <q who="#JB">Finally, I sent you another email last week (July 7) with the subject "A few more quick questions (when you have time)" with some questions that I think might have gotten lost in your inbox. I sent it to you before you answered the previous one (I wrote it meaning to save it until later but sent it by mistake, sorry). </q> It didnꞌt get lost.  I have it.  I was not feeling well last week and besides I was preparing some reading and writing lessons in Mixtec as your request.  Also I have been working on the appropriate abbreviations I will use to gloss the pronouns that I have send to our linguistic consultant and I am almost finishing with that (God willing).  I am working on a paper and I have to turn the draft on September.  So I am organizing the data, putting texts on a text program to do the interlinear and all these things take time.
            I have been working also on the orthography, especially tone orthography (on verbs).  Verbs have a high tone on the first syllable and we said that we will put an acute accent on the vowel of that syllable.  Now I feel that this is redundant, since we can identify them without tone marking.  One example is the one you mentioned above.  Just that I think you have a combination of two words which mean "to sing".  The basic form is "
            <seg xml:id="d1e135" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e136">kata</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e138">yaa</w>
            </seg>"
            which literally means, to 
            <spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e135" xml:lang="en">sing</span>
               
               <span target="#d1e136" xml:lang="en">sing</span>
               <span target="#d1e138" xml:lang="en">the music</span>
            </spanGrp>".  
            "<seg xml:id="d1e147" xml:lang="mix" type="declarative">
               <w xml:id="d1e148">Tsita</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e150">yu</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e152">yaa</w>
            </seg>."
            (<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e147" xml:lang="en">I am singing</span>
            </spanGrp>);
            "<seg xml:id="d1e160" xml:lang="mix" type="declarative">
               <w xml:id="d1e161">Ntsita</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e163">yu</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e165">yaa</w>
            </seg>."
            (<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1e160" xml:lang="en">I sang</span>
            </spanGrp>.); 
            "<seg xml:id="d1f165">
               <w xml:id="d1e172">Kunkata</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e174">yu</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e176">yaa</w>
            </seg>." 
            (<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#d1f165" xml:lang="en">I will sing.</span>
            </spanGrp>);"
            <seg xml:id="d1e184" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e185">Kata</w><pc>!</pc>
            </seg>" 
            <note ana="#TONE">(with MM tone)</note>.  See?  There are many verbs like that. 
            
            My concern is causatives verbs and iteratives (repetitives).  The form of the imperfective and perfective aspect is the same but the tone change.  The imperfective aspect for causatives has a high tone on the first syllable and the perfective has a rising tone.  The latter is the one that Mixtec people associates with an acute accent.  I sent a note to the orthography consultant about this, but I havenꞌt received a word.  I am letting you know about this so you know that the tone orthography could change.
            
            On Monday and Tuesday I will be working and recording verbs with a Mixtec guy who will come to the ling. center where I am, since I want to confirm the tones of the causatives and other items.  In Mixtec is very common to find floating tones because of the deletion of vowels and syllables.  Causatives are one example.  But since I havenꞌt done an exhaustive analysis on tone I will do the recording of items that I consider very important for the orthography.  
            
            <q who="#JB">Tatsa'vi ni inka tuku!</q>
            <seg xml:id="d1e190" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e191">Tatsaꞌvi</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e193">meu</w>
            </seg>.
            
            <q who="#JB">Sana ka'an</q>
            <seg xml:id="d1e198" xml:lang="mix"><!-- @type? -->
               <w xml:id="d1e199">Sana</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e201">kaꞌan</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e203">nunuu</w>
            </seg>
            <q who="#JB">Jack</q>
            Na Millie ‑ Mixtec people from <placeName>Santa María Teposlantongo</placeName>, one of the  "agencias" of Mixtepec do not use the <span target="#" xml:lang="">formal pronoun</span> "<seg xml:id="d1e215" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e216">na</w>
            </seg>", instead they use "<seg xml:id="d1e219" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e220">ña</w>
            </seg>".  So even young people would refer to me by <seg xml:id="d1e223" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e224">ña</w>
               <persName>Millie</persName>
            </seg>.  Also they would use <seg xml:id="d1e229" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e230">
                  <c>‑</c>ku</w>
            </seg>, <seg xml:id="d1e235" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e236">
                  <c>‑</c>u</w>
            </seg>; the equivalent "<span target="#" xml:lang="">tú</span>" in <lang>Spanish</lang>.  This is only in <placeName full="abb">SMT</placeName>.  Just to let you know these differences.
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

