<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence Mille 20170708</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Speaker</resp>
               <name xml:id="MN">Mille Nieves</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Jack Bowers</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName>Mille Nieves</persName>
               <date>2018/07/08</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="recieved">
               <persName>Jack Bowers</persName>
               <date>2018/07/08</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <note>Mixtepec-Mixtec language and sources discussion</note>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>Hi Mille, 
            <lb/>Thank you for the Reyes document I didn't have that and did not know about
            it! I would very much be interested in the Alvarado document as well if you could
            manage! One more question about demonstrative pronouns: I have 'naká' labeled as
            3pl.formal (again from the description of one of my speakers early on in the process)
            but I think that might be wrong. No, he is not wrong. The clitic “na” is a formal
            pronoun. Again, pronouns and clitics are better described on the discourse. Precisely
            Iꞌm writing a paper on participant reference but it will take some time while I
            interlinearize and analyze the texts, write the paper, consulting, etc. &gt; We describe it
            as 3pl.for (formal), and can be used for either gender and has no formality register is
            that right? I explained above. I havenꞌt finish the revision of the orthography which I
            owe you and Iꞌm planning to give it to you with a brief description of the grammar. Both
            of us need the orthography. So I want to finish its revision and get some answers from
            the orthography consultant. The final product wonꞌt be an established orthography, but
            at least it will be polished and better than we have now. Once I have the orthography
            ready, I can work on some lessons. Today I am waiting for an answer from the orth.
            consultant. Next week I can finish the revision and work on the lessons. I just need to
            work on that only, because it takes times. Since I have to write and edit, takes a time.
            In summary, next week I will finish the revision of the orth. and some lessons in
            Mixtec. I have a list of the pronouns for you. I will revise them too and give them to
            you. I also have some notes on the Mixtec grammar to accompany the orthography.
            Regarding "want" 'kuni': Your theory is interesting because I had also seen a connection
            with the potential copula, but I had figured the reverse order e.g that "kun- + ni"
            existed first and "want" is a compound of the two, with 'ni' being the same as is used
            to mark the completive. So I saw this as kind of abstract mixing of the sense of
            potential reality and past reality then combining it with a person marker made it
            express the will of that person. I'd be interested in hearing more arguments for your
            theory though. In the way I'm encoding my data I can make separate etymologies for
            different theories for any given word and can attribute it so I can do this for "kuni"
            and attribute it to you. I am not sure if this is the same word; who knows what happen
            here Jack. The old word for the copula was “kuvui”. I think in Mixtepec was “kuvi”.
            Probably what it has occurred is that “vi” was deleted and the “u” from “ku‑” was
            lengthened. This phonological process is very common across the Mixteca. Also, “ku‑” can
            be attached to another morpheme. But the “kuni” I am talking about doesnꞌt seem to me
            that is the copula plus “ni” compl. Although the copula could be attached to “ni” or to
            other morpheme. I think that what happens here is that the copula be, “kuu” deletes the
            last “u” and is attached to some adjectives to form verbs. This is a derivational
            process where an adjective becomes a (intransitive) verb which indicates a change of a
            state. <table rows="4" cols="4">
               <head/>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell>Verbo</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Adjetivo</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e57" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e58">kusii</w>
                        <w xml:id="d1e60">ini</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">to be happy</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">alegrarse</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e72" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e73">sii</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en">happy</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">alegre</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e86" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e87">ku‑iya</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">turn sour</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">ponerse agrio</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e99" xml:lang="mix">iya</seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">sour</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">agrio</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e112" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e113">ntuvii</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">to clean</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">limpiarse</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e125" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e126">vii</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">clean</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">limpio</span>
                     </spanGrp>,<spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en" resp="#JB">shiny</span>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">brillante</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e145" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e146">ntukatsi</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en"/>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">endurecerse</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <seg xml:id="d1e157" xml:lang="mix">
                        <w xml:id="d1e158">katsi</w>
                     </seg>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <spanGrp type="translation">
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="en"/>
                        <span target="#" xml:lang="es">duro</span>
                     </spanGrp>
                     <spanGrp type="gram">
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                        <span type="" target="#" ana="#"/>
                     </spanGrp>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <lb/>
            <lb/> Normally, “ni” does appear as a prefix to indicate completive aspect in most of
            the Mixtec varieties. But I know that at least in Santa María Zacatepec Mixtec, “ni”
            indicates the opposite; the potential aspect. So here it seems to me that in Zacatepec
            the prefix “ni” for future comes from kuni. Also, tone is important to distinguish all
            these “niꞌs” If you compare the different Mixtec grammars, you will realize that
            sometimes grammatical categories (or grammatical profiles) are used in the same way
            across the Mixteca but not necessarily. Even in Mixtepec you could see that, even when
            is only one language area among other Mixtec language areas. For example, Mixtec people
            in Mixtepec use the clitic “ni” to refer to older people, important people, among other
            contexts. However, in Santa María Teposlantongo, one of the “agencias” of Mixtepec,
            Mixtec people use “ku” “meu” instead (for everyone). I think that before you reach a
            conclusion, you should compare the different Mixtec grammars and different Mixtec
            dictionaries, compare your lexical items against Alvaradoꞌs vocabulary, just to see the
            language some centuries ago. I encourage you to read Jansenꞌs analysis of Alvaradoꞌs
            vocabulary and other items he has written. Also, be familiar with the different
            phonological processes in Mixtec. Do you have other Mixtec grammars and dictionaries
            from SIL? If not, let me know. I can send them to you. The grammars written in SIL are
            written for native speakers who can handle Spanish. So the use of technical terms are
            avoided. Still it is difficult for native speakers of Mixtec. There was a linguist who
            wrote a book on the Mixtec (phonemes?) reconstruction. I donꞌt remember if she included
            a grammar too. His name is Kathryn Josserand. She passed away in 2006. I donꞌt have the
            book but she did a comparative study on some Mixtec varieties. Material for my speakers:
            So I have some good news (that I hope will be finalized in the next day or so), and that
            is that thanks to some generous funding from my PhD advisor and the organization he
            runs, I will be bringing one of my speakers to Austria to work for a week and travel a
            bit after. This is instead of paying him as I was trying to do and it's a way to thank
            him for his time he has put in in helping me as the work has already given me so many
            opportunities, in my professional life and PhD. These will be good news for your
            coworker. Iꞌm glad you can remunerate him. Anyway, among other things, I plan on having
            him help me gloss some of the SIL texts that I'm not able to do on my own and transcribe
            some spoken language into the orthography. As you've discussed from your experience, he,
            like many other Mixtecs isn't totally consistant in his use of the written language and
            doesn't always distinguish the key things like "a'a" vs "aa", "a'an" vs "aan" etc. They
            are not conscious of the written glottal stop. Also, sometimes they speak so fast that
            they donꞌt pronounce the glottal, although they say they do. I wonder if the “h” that
            many linguists used many years ago works for the glottal. In Silacayoapan Mixtec the
            linguists and Mixtec people still use the “h” instead the glottal ( ꞌ ). I would like to
            get him up to date on some of the orthographic conventions that have been changed since
            the SIL publication that we have discussed (tone, minimal distinctions etc.) So I was
            wondering if you might have some documents, exercises, etc. that you have used that I
            could send him to study up on before he gets here and that he can use as a reference? (I
            do of course already have the Guía Ortográfica Preliminar which should help). Remember
            that you have only one part of the Guía... I expect to have all this work (including the
            excercises) done by the 17th with the rest of the documents I said I will send you. If I
            have everything ready before the 17, I will send it to you before that date. It's of
            course ok if you're busy working with your colleague and can't get back to me, none of
            these questions are super urgent and I appreciate whenever you have time to help me
            which you have been very generous about. Thank you Jack. I just need time to write. Also
            I got a cold and I am working with one speed. Every Tuesday I have a 1‑2 hours meeting
            plus some linguistic work I want to complete during the week. So thatꞌs why there will
            be some times that I wonꞌt be available; perhaps one day or one week. I am glad to serve
            you and to serve other people. Tatsa'vi ni! <seg xml:id="d1e171" xml:lang="mix">
               <w xml:id="d1e172">Tatsaꞌvi</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e174">meu</w>
            </seg>. (<spanGrp type="translation">
               <span target="#" xml:lang="en">Thanks to you too.</span>
            </spanGrp>) Jack Na
            Millie PD ‑ I attached a book from Marteen Jansen. Hope you can find it useful. If not
            you can always delete it.</ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
