<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence Mille Nieves 2017/07/28</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="MN">Mille Nieves</persName>
               <date>2017.07.28</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="recieved">
               <persName resp="JB">Jack Bowers</persName>
               <date>2017.07.28</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <note></note>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            Hi,
            
            See below.
            
            On 7/28/2017 9:09 AM, Jack Bowers wrote:
            Hi Mille,
            
            Thanks again for the very helpful explanations! Sorry to come back so fast, I of course understand if you can't get back for any given reason. I hope your move went well and you got your program fixed successfully last week!
            
            I've gotten some of the Cruxigrammas glossed by one of my consultants but I'm still probably doing about 45% of the rest and so naturally I have some things I was hoping you could help me with. 
            
            
            (1)
            yee (≈ haber) vs kumi (have)? Yee means,to exist  and to live  but sometimes means to have.   But "kumi" always means to have.
            
            One sentence is:
            
            "Kiti yo'o yii yuku ra yee ntikia"
            'this animal has a horn'
            Este animal vive en el monte y tiene cuernos.
            
            The other is:
            
            "Nto'o luulu ntiyaa kumia ra kanti"
            'It has a very small tail and jumps'
            (El animal) tiene una colita y salta (el animal).
            I> 
            What is the difference between the usage and meaning of these verbs? See above.
            
            >'yee' is often used like es. 'hay' right? So why use it in that first sentence?  Well, usually Mixtec people would say, "Así no más hablamos."
            
            (2)
            itsi
            
            This is generally 'insect' but it seems to also be used in describing other things (that fly)?
            A hint for what is "kolo" 'male turkey' is:
            
            "in itsi ka'nu vi ra, kumia tumi"
            "a big (insect!?) that/it has feathers"
            Un  animal grande, (y) tiene plumas.
            
            >Why is "itsi" used and not "saa" or 'kiti"? The word "itsi" primarily means "insect", but it is also used as a general word for any kind of animal.  They could not used "saaꞌ or "kiti" because this is a cross word puzzle and the reader have to guess the solution.  So this is not a normal (natural) sentence. 
            
            (3)
            Tsachoon vs Tsachuun
            
            My consultant tends to translate "tsachoon" as 1sg but I see no indication of 1st person
            
            > is this correct? 
            
            > Are they the same verbs or is "to use" and "to work" different? They are the same verb but the first one is 1pl.incl. (Usamos). The second one should be the basic form (usar).  The word "trabajamos" should be sachoon and the basic form should be "sachuun".
            
            e.g 
            "Tsachoon ña ta kuskee"
            "I* use it when I unhusk the corn"
            "Lo usamos cuando vamos a cosechar."
            "We use it when we are going to harvest (corn)."
            
            "Kue ña'a ña tsachoon"
            "things I use"
            Things we use.
            
            (4)
            Forms of 'eat'
            
            I've come across a verb form of "eat" that I don't recognize:
            
            While the familiar form of eat is "tsatsi" (infinitive "katsi") below there is "tsaki"
            
            "Ntikuii vi cha skuachi na ña cha tsaki na ña nuu nchai"
            "It's green and chopped up and is eaten on food"
            Lit. Es verde y lo  pican  y lo echan a la comida.
            
            >Is this still the verb "katsi"? No. The word tsaki means "poner" and here it means "echar".
            
            >If so, what aspect/form is it?  This is the incompletive aspect (or imperfective) but it is used as the habitual aspect.
            
            also
            
            > is the "vi" here the pronoun  (~ kui) we were discussing?  It is the copula with the pronoun "i".  
            
            > if yes, why is it used here over other options? The function is to affirm that the thing the reader has to guess is green.
            
            
            (5)
            iin as "have"?
            
            In one of the Cruxigramas pages the hint is:
            
            "Yee ka'ni nta'a tu cha iin iñu ña" Here I think that here is not "kaꞌni", but "kani" long.  It is a mistake.
            "There are/it has big branches and thorns" (my rough english translation)
            
            My speaker glossed "iin" as "have", It means "estar", but it is used as "tener".  He is right.  I would say that this is a kind of copula.
            
            > is the yet another "ii/iin"?!  Yes, and it contrasts with "iꞌin" steam bath.
            
            
            Tatsa'vi ni!  Sana kaꞌan toko.
            
            Jack
            na Millie
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

