<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            THE PHONOLOGY
            OF THE MIXTEPEC DIALECT OF MIXTEC
            EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
            1. PHONOLOGICAL WORD
            In Mixtepec Mixtec1 the minimal phonological word is made up of the sequence of two syllables - a couplet. This couplet is the complex nucleus of the word; the first syllable is marked phonologically by a lengthened vowel unless that vowel is preceding /?/: k[o.^lo^ko1 'our (excl.) male turkey', s[i.Ysiz-ei2 'his or her (child) aunt', .]3ko3-yu3 'my (polite) collarbone', ζ,[ΐ.]ΗαΖΛ 'sandal\ tizkw[a.]za2 'butterfly'; but, la?2la2-ei2 'his or her (child) mucus', ja1 ^al-m1 'your (sing, polite) gravy'.
            A hyphen has been placed after the couplet unless the couplet is final in the word. For example: ka1suz-nir 'you (sing, polite) are toasting (it)' versus tizkazsuz 'a toasted tortilla'; kaza2-ei2 'his or her (child) metal' versus vexkaza2 'a jail'; eizso2-ei2 'his or her (child) brother-in- law' versus 0izkuzci2 'a bat'; taxku2ni2 'yesterday' versus talkat-ni1 'your (sing, polite) woodpecker'.
            Following are a few examples of nouns made up of the fusion of two couplets: ve2?e2 'house' + c|2y2 'work' > νε2£{ιφ 'townhall'; da2?a1 'hand' + ka3a2 'metal' > daxka3a2 'key'; so3?o2 'ear' + ve2?e2 'house' > so3ve2?e2 'side of house'; doz?o2 'adobe' + ya2ta\ 'old' > do3ya2tal 'old adobe'; svs'19V2 'money' + tu2tu3 'paper' > s\i31tu2tu3 'paper money'.
            Timing is one of the contrastive features of the phonological word in that a word with several syllables is usually pronounced faster than words with only two syllables. Syllables which occur post-couplet are pronounced especially fast.
            Examples of words with four or more syllables: ti3ku3mi2-yu3 'my (polite) onion', kwi3kaz-ko2yi3 'their (masc. fam.) comb', dfitq^^-ni1 'you (sing, polite) are stingy', eaPnfikfisfi-ni1 'you (sing, polite) already slept', ku1ni3duHi2-ko2yiz 'they (masc. fam.) will bury (it)', ku^si^ko2- ko2yux 'you (pi. fam.) will sell', m3ni3ka2da1 va3ei2-ra3 'they (masc.
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            ￼272 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
            polite) already came again', da1si3-1ko2-tu2ku2ko2yu1 'you (pi. fam.) are going to sell again'.
            Loudness, stress, usually occurs on the first syllable of the couplet. When, however, tone 1 or tone 2 precedes tone 3, the syllable preceding the tone 3 may be louder than the first syllable: v/1/m1-jw3 'my (polite) cat', ei3so2-yu3 'my (polite) brother-in-law'. The loudness is especially noticeable on the tone clusters 1-3 and 2-3: vfilu1'3 'my (fam.) cat', 0i3so2-3 'my (fam.) brother-in-law'. The contrast between sa3-2a3 'beard' and ka3a2 3 'my (fam.) bell' can be perceived both as a difference in placement of stress, and as the lower allotone of tone 2 in sa32a3 versus the raised allotone of tone 2 in ka3a2_3. See § 4 for a discussion of allo- tones.
            2. SYLLABLE
            The first syllable of the couplet consists of one vowel preceded by one or two consonants. It may or may not be followed by a glottal stop. This syllable has either a single tone, or a cluster of two tones. Examples of the various types of syllables initial in the couplet: CV+CV eo^ko2
            'possum', n2ta3 'flower', tP W 'dog', ki^nfl 'pig', φΛψ
            C V + C V sa?23va3 'frog', fe?2/w2 'lamb'; CCV+CV sk^ko1 turning (it)', sku31ci2 'bathed', sci^i3 'is grinding'; CCV+CV 'is causing to enter'.
            'rat'; 'is ski^vi2
            The second syllable of the couplet consists of one or two vowels which may or may not be preceded by one (not two) consonants. This syllable has either a single tone, or a cluster of two tones. Examples of the various types follow: CV+V lu2u2 'small', ^ο.ΖΛα2 'new', η/2 3/1 'ear of corn', m-2-3/i-3 'my (fam>) gar of corn'; CV+CV si^ni3-1 'hat'; CV+?V ÄU3-2?M3 'fire'; CV+CV ka^nu2 'big'; CV+CW si^nia3^ 'her (fam.) hat', sil znia\-z 'his (fam.) hat', yu3ltial 'her (fam.) sand', v/1/«/1 'her (fam.) cat', v/1/«/1"3 'his (fam.) cat'; CCV+V stcPu1 'your (sing, fam.) tortilla'.
            We consider the sequence of two vowels which occur after the couplet- medial consonant to be one syllable and not two since they are short, and since the tone sequences 2 1 and 1 2 can occur in successive syllables, but do not occur on the vowels in that environment. The only vowel sequences which occur in the second syllable are /ia/ and /ui/.
            For the most part, only the syllable type CV occurs pre or post-couplet. For example: ni3ki3si3 'slept', villul-kul 'your (sing, fam.) cat'. But see sta30a3'1a3'1 'liver'.
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            ￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 273 3. TONE CONTRAST
            There are three levels of tone: 1 (high), 2 (mid), 3 (low). These contrast as in: eqlpyx 'y°u (sing, fam.) are smoking', eq1?y2 'is smoking',
            Ί (fam.) am smoking'; kwi3ka3-nix 'your (sing, polite) comb', kwi3ka3-ei2
            'his or her (child) comb', kwi3ka3-ra3 'his (polite) comb'. Contrasts can also be demonstrated following the frames: 9i2p 'one', ?i3i3 'nine'; and when preceding kannu2 'big'. For example: yuxku3 'yoke', tu2tu3 'paper', kwi3ka3 'comb'; saxta2i dove', ma2cu2 'mule', ei3so2 'brother- in-law'.
            In two-syllable words with a medial consonant, eight different se- quences of single tones occur: lolcil 'buzzard', eoxko2 'possum', suxku3 'high'; ya2tax 'old', ya2ci2 'near', si2to3 'uncle'; si3kwi2 'milk', so3ko3 'collarbone'. The tone sequence 3 1 may occur when the second syllable consists of a vowel: ko3ox 'snake'. When, however, there is a medial consonant, the sequence 3 1 alternates to 3-2 1 and 3-1 1 as in: ji3!3' 2/3-ifcMi 'you (sing, fam.) are returning'. When the tone sequence 3 1 occurs between words, however, that alternation does not occur: tu2tu3
            Jaxax 'blue paper', kwi3ka3 kannu2 'big comb'.
            We have distinguished between a TONE SEQUENCE in which the tones
            occur on successive syllables and a TONE CLUSTER in which the tones occur on a single syllable. There are four tone clusters: 3-1, 3-2, 1-3, and 2-3. The clusters 2-1 and 1-2 do not occur. The cluster 3-2 does not occur on a word-final syllable. Following are examples showing single tone and tone clusters in contrast.
            Tone sequences beginning with tone 1: kollox~3 'my (fam.) male turkey', kaxsu3'x 'you (sing, fam.) sneeze', eaxku3 X 'you (sing, fam.) are placing (it)', eaxku3 'is placing (it)', koxlox 'male turkey', suxku3 'high'. The cluster 2-3 does not follow tone 1.
            Tone sequences beginning with the tone cluster 1-3: tux-3eix3 Ί (fam.) have pain', tux-3ei3'x 'has pain', eax zku3 x 'you (sing, fam.) are laughing', mx'zku3 'is laughing', eix'3ni2 'is intoxicated', eix-3ni2-3 Ί (fam.) am in- toxicated', skex'3tux 'you (sing, fam.) ran quickly'.
            Tone sequences beginning with tone 2: ya2tix-3 'he (fam.) is old', si2su3'x 'your (sing, fam.) aunt', ta2six 'quiet', ya2ci2 'near', si2si3 'aunt'. The cluster 2-3 does not follow tone 2.
            Tone sequences beginning with the tone cluster 2-3: sa^2'3mix-3 'his (fam.) clothing', sa92'3ma3-x 'clothing', yu2-3ci3 'knife'. The tones 1 and 2 and the cluster 2-3 do not follow tone cluster 2-3.
            Tone sequences beginning with tone 3: na3max-3 'my (fam.) soap',
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            274 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
            0a3tu31 'box', ti30i2-3 'my (fam.) stomach', yu3ca2 'river', su3tu3 'priest'.
            Tone sequences beginning with the tone cluster 3-2 or with the tone cluster 3-1: ko32su31 'your (sing, fam.) adze', ji32ko2 '(someone) ground (it)', da3-2kus 'broom', ^3/3-2/3-1^1 'looked for', du3'3-2^ ku1-3 Ί (fam.) looked for', yu3-lti2 'sand', yu3lti3 'my (fam.) sand'. The cluster 2-3 does not follow the cluster 3-2 or 3-1.
            In couplets without a medial consonant, nine different sequences of single tones occur: ja^a1 'blue', stoxo2 'is erasing', kwq1q3 'yellow', je2ex 'thick', lu2u2 'small', sa2a3 'bird', sta3cl· 'tortilla', ca3a2 'man',
            da3a3 'straight'.
            The tone clusters 1-3, 3-1, 3-2, 2-3 may also occur in couplets with
            no medial consonants: q13^1 'fingernail', cil zil z 'my (fam.) fingernail', 0a31u1 'you (sing, fam.) are young', eaZAa2 'new', ζαΖΛα? Ί (fam.) am young', v/2'3/1 'pretty', ν/2 3/1"3 Ί (fam.) am pretty', Vi1 "3 my (fam.) hail', pali31 'her (fam.) bread', je2e1'3 Ί (fam.) am thick', p/2w3"1 'your (sing, fam.) badger', jo3*?1"3 'my (fam.) blanket', ka3u3-1 'your (sing, fam.) bell', sa3-2a3 'beard'.
            Even when the vowels are contiguous, there is contrastive placement of three tones on the two syllables. That is, there is contrastive placement of a tone cluster plus a single tone versus a single tone plus a tone cluster versus a tone cluster plus a tone cluster. For example: sta3a1-3 'my (fam.) tortilla', versus wz la3 Ί (fam.) am young'; yw23/1 'her (fam.) bird', versus nu2i31 'her (fam.) town'; stazul 'your (sing, fam.) tortilla', versus 0a3'1u1 'you (sing, fam.) are young', versus da3uzx 'you (sing, fam.) are correct' (also: ja3"2«31 'your (sing, fam.) beard', Sa32a3 'beard', versus ka3a2'3 'my (fam.) bell'; ka3a2 'bell', da3a3 'straight', sa2a3 'bird').
            Several of the sets of words differing by tone are as follows: νa3?a2 'good', να31?α2 'bad'; va3?M31 'you (sing, fam.) are good', να3"1?«1 'you (sing, fam.) are bad'; ?i1l1 'hail', ?i2i2 'one', 'nine',
            'skin', ψΐ1 'salt', ?ΐψ 'there are', W 3 'my (fam.) hail', ψ ψ 3 'my (fam.) skin', 'my (fam.) salt'; difiku1 'is looking for', di^ku1 'will soon look for', du2kux-3 Ί (fam.) am looking for', dxfl-ku1-3 Ί (fam.)
            will soon look for', du3-2kux 'looked for', du3-2kux~3 Ί (fam.) looked for'; tu2tu3 'paper', tu2tu3-x 'your (sing, fam.) paper', tu2'3tw3*1 'firewood', tu2~3tux~3 'my (fam.) firewood', tu13tu31 'is whistling'; tux'3tux·3 Ί (fam.) am whistling'; w31ku2 'corral', 0azlkuz 'my (fam.) corral', 0a3 iku31 'your (sing, fam.) corral', 0al 3ku3 'is laughing', 0a1'3ku31 'you (sing, fam.) are laughing', 0alku3 'is placing (it)', 0axku31 'you (sing, fam.) are placing (it)'.
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            ￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 275 4. TONE VARIANTS
            Tone variants may be conditioned by the vowel with which the tone occurs. The vowel /if usually has a higher pitch than the other vowels in the same environments: va3ei2 su3tu3 'a priest is coming' versus ku3na2 su3tu3 'a priest is opening (it)'; du2ku1-ko2yi1 'they (fem. fam.) are looking for' versus du2kux-ko2yux 'you (pi. fam.) are looking for';
            i-3 ' m y (fam.) leg' versus s p ' h i s (fam.) leg'; tq19q3 'my (fam.) relative' versus tql p{'3 'his (fam.) relative'.
            Lower allotones frequently occur with nasal vowels: cjj3y2 'hen', versus yu3u2 'stone'; kwix'3ix 'narrow' versus k«tfi-3/ι 'green'.
            Even within repetitions of the same word, there is considerable variation in the pitch of tone 1.
            Tone 1 has a raised allotone when contiguously preceding tone 2, and it is raised even higher when preceding tone 3: kollox ka91nu2 'big male turkey', tixsix eolko2 'a possum is whining' (the third syllables are the highest); koxlox-ra3 'his (polite) male turkey', koxlox-ei2 'his or her (child) male turkey' (the second syllables are the highest).
            When two clusters of 1-3 occur in the same word, the first has the higher allotone: kal'3sa13 Ί (fam.) am sneezing', six-3ni13 'my (fam.) hat'.
            Tone 1 is lowered when it occurs as part of the tone cluster 3-1. The tone cluster 3-1 varies between a short upglide and a level allotone: ku3mi3-xya2?ax 'four eagles'. (See the paragraph on the description of the allotones of the 3-1 cluster for further details of the variants.)
            Tone 2 has a raised allotone when contiguously preceding tone 3: le92lu2-ras 'his (polite) lamb' (the second syllable is the highest).
            When part of the tone cluster 3-2, the tone 2 is lowered: ti32na3 'dog', du3~2si3 'honey', sa32a3 'beard'. (See the paragraph on the description of the allotones of the 3-2 cluster for further details of the variants.)
            A tone 3 is lower when part of a prepause tone sequence 3 2 than when it is part of a nonprepause 3 2 sequence: va3ei2ei3soz 'a brother-in-law is coming', kP3vi2kwa39a2 '(his) brother is entering' (the third syllables are lowest).
            A phrase-final tone 3 may downglide. It may vary from a short to a longer downglide when, as part of the same word, it follows the tone cluster 3-1. There is still a contrast, however, between a long downgliding allotone of tone 3, and a downgliding 1-3, or 2-3 cluster: yu3'xtia3 'his (fam.) sand' versus ka3ciax-3 'his (fam.) cotton' versus ti3eia2'3 'his (fam.) stomach'. (See the paragraph on the allotones of the cluster 3-1.)
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            ￼276 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
            Tone 3 usually has a longer downglide when following a cluster 3-1 than when following tone 1 or the cluster 3-2: A;o1/o1-ra3 'his (polite) maleturkey'versuska3ci31-ra3 'his(polite)cotton'versus ku3 2 nu3
            'meat'.
            The tone cluster 3-1 varies from an upglide, sometimes short, sometimes
            long, to a level tone which is lower than a normal tone 2.
            When followed within the word by a tone 3, the cluster 3-1 alternates between an upglide and a level tone. When the cluster 3-1 is a level pitch, the following tone 3 is a downglide which starts higher than the phonetic level of the cluster 3-1. When the cluster 3-1 is actualized as an upglide, the downglide of the tone 3 does not start as high as the end of the cluster 3-1: ka3 ci3 1 -ra3 'his (polite) cotton', ea3 tu3 1 -yu3 'my (polite) box'; yo^io3 'my(fam.)metate',k u 1 ^ 3 ' 1 ^ 3 Ί (fam.)willsell', kul gw is -2 so3
            Ί (fam.) will carry', k ^ g u h u 3 Ί (fam.) will sleep'.
            When followed by a tone 3 in the following word, the cluster 3-1
            isactualizedbyanupglide:ta3 ta3 1 ?u3 va3 'bittermedicine'; m?3 νϊ3 Λ -τα3 'his(polite)chewinggum'versusea?3 vi3 J-vi3 si3 'sweetchewinggum'.
            When followed within the word by a tone 2, the cluster 3-1 glides to a level higher than the following tone 2: y o 3 1 s o 2 'metate'; k a 3 c i 3 1 - e i 2 'his or her (child) cotton' versus k i 3 s i 2 - e i 2 'his or her (child) jar' versus
            sa3 0i3 -?i2 'hisorher(child)nephew'.
            When followed by a tone 1, there is no contrast between a cluster 3-1
            andacluster3-2:0a3tu3-2l31-na1 'her(polite)box'versus cPto^na1 'her (polite) bed'; ka3 ci3 '2 !3 1 -ni1 'your (sing, polite) cotton' versus k i 3 s i 2 - n i l 'your (sing, polite) jar' versus s a 3 0 i 3 - n i 1 'your (sing, polite) nephew';su3 '2 l3 -1 ko1 lo1 -kw i1 -3 'itisnotamaleturkey', su3 -1 le^2 lu2 -kw i1 -3
            'it is not a lamb'.
            Tone cluster 3-2 varies from a short upglide to a level pitch which is
            justhigherthantone3:ji3 -2 ci3 'stringbean',ti3 2 na3 'dog'.
            Because the allotones of tone 3 and clusters 3-2 and 3-1 are so varied, and because (until a person is aware of the environments in which the allotones occur) contrast is hard to hear, we have given additional contrastive sets: z i 3 - 2 k a 2 '(someone)walked', y o 3 1 s o 2 'metate'; d a 3 2 k u 3 'broom',e a 3 1 k u 3 'my(fam.)corral',ea3 tu3 'hot,spicy',ea2 tu3 'trousers', sal nu3 'my(fam.)cigar';di3~2vu31 'you(sing,fam.)blew', stu^vu3 '1 'you (sing, fam.) knocked down', d u 3 e u 3 X 'you (sing, fam.) have pain', d t f v u 3 ' 1 'your (sing, fam.) vegetable', s f i v u 3 1 'your (sing, fam.) name'; ni3 ka3 2 ci3 '(someone) said', 0a3 sci3 1 ?i3 '(someone) already ground'.
            Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
            ￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 277 5. CONSONANT CONTRASTS
            In this dialect of Mixtec there are six voiceless unaspirated stops or affricates /p (rare), t, φ, c, k, kw/, a glottal stop /Ύ, six voiced prenasalized stops or affricates /b (rare), d, j, g, gw (rare)/, two voiceless sibilants /s, s (retroflexed)/, two semi-consonants /v, y/, three nasals /m, η, η/, a lateral /I/, and a flap /r/.
            Bilabials /p, b, v, m/: /jü1^3 'bread', όα1«3 'compadre', να3?α2 'good', ίΗθ1?α3 'raccoon'.
            Dentals /t, φ, d, s, η, 1, r/: ta3ta31 'medicine', da3a3 'straight', ea31a2 'new', zannu2 'old person', ία2α3 'bird', na2-3^1 'to carry-in- arms', la?2la2 'mucus'. The flap /r/ occurs only in a few morphemes other than Spanish loan words, but it contrasts, with /I/ and with jtj in: ft/V«1 'burro' versus lu2lu2 'small' versus Λ'1/«1 'kid'.
            Alveopalatals /c, j, s, y, η/: ca3a2 'man', y^a1 'blue', sa32a3 'beard', ya\-3al 'tongue', na29a1 'woman'. There is contrast between /δ/ and ΙΦΙ in ίϊ3Λά2 'avocado' versus ti3ci2 'stomach'; and between /]/ and /?/ in jVci3 'difficult' versus zi3ca3-x 'sandals'.
            Velars and glottal stop /k, kw, g, gw, £α2&α3 'lime', kwa3?a2 '(his) sister', ga32a3 'town of Putla', gwi2i2 'fox', kwi13il 'green', W 'five'. The glottal stop contrasts with the absence of glottal stop and with /t/: 'five', /y3^1 'charcoal', 'word'. A labialized velar stop contrasts with /ku/: kwix'3il 'green' versus ku2il 'she is able to'.
            6. CONSONANT VARIANTS
            The consonant /k/ varies from a voiceless velar stop to a voiced lenis fricative [g], and the consonant jyj varies from a voiced alveopalatal resonant to a lenis fricative [z] when they occur following the couplet: v/1/«1-[k/g]«1 'your (sing, fam.) cat', v/W-fco^y/z]/3 'their (masc. fam.) cat'.
            The consonant j\j varies from labiodental to bilabial. The labiodental allophone is more frequent when contiguous to jij and /e/; whereas the bilabial allophone is more frequent when contiguous to /a/: sfivi31
            'name', da3va2 'to fly', vi3ei2 'cold', va3?a2 'good', να3«1 'joint'.
            A couplet-medial consonant may be lengthened in emphatic speech:
            skex[L.]a2 'run!', jil[s.]o2 'carry (it)!'.
            7. VOWEL CONTRASTS
            There are five oral vowels /i, e, a, o, u/ and five nasal vowels /[, ς, <? (one morpheme only), y/. Sets of words showing the contrasts follow.
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼278 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
With medial glottal stop: \i2Hz 'his (fam.) house', ve2?e2 'house', V f l 3 ? f l 2 'good', yo2?ol 'rope', yu2?ul 'mouth'; s[3'forked limb', (/ς/ does not occur following /?/), 'a relative', £ρ3?ρ31 'we (excl.) are going', ky3?^3 'is going', scficpiß· 'is working', s^cp-g1 'we (excl.) are working'.
With no medial consonant: ?/2/3 'badger', ve3e2 'heavy', caza2 'man', yozox 'moon', yu3ul 'stone'; ?i2i2 'one', ίςζξ2 'perspiration', cq2q3 'forehead', ίς3ςι 'our (excl. fam.) charcoal', iy3^1 'charcoal'.
With medial /k/: ?ΐ2-3Ιά3Λ 'squash' (/e/ does not follow a medial /k/), talka2 'woodpecker', eolko2 'possum', sulkuz 'high'. Except for /?/, nasal vowels do not follow a medial consonant.
8. VOWEL VARIANTS
A vowel, a sequence of vowels, and vowels separated by /?/ become allophonically nasalized when following a nasal consonant: ny2 [ημ2?μ1] 'land'. This allophonic nasalization, however, is not as heavy as the nasalization of a nasal vowel: ηα2 Άαι 'dark' versus kwqlq3 'yellow', n/2-3/i 4 e a r 0 f corn' versus 'skin', sil znial z 'his (fam.) hat' versus ή·ι-3^ι-3 'his ( f a m . ) fingernails'. Vowels have very little allophonic nasalization when preceding a nasal consonant: k^mi3'1 'four', ki23ni3
'pig'. The vowel /u/ is more heavily nasalized than other vowels: nifiu1 'face' versus ni3il 'blood', ncfi ^a1 'dark,' eq3^3 'fifteen'.
All vowels (except those preceding /?/) have lengthened allophones when occurring in the first syllable of the couplet: ki3si2 'jar', suztuz 'priest', sozkoz 'collarbone', salta2 'dove', ske1ta2 'is running quickly'. Because of the /?/, the vowel of the first syllable is not lengthened as in
the following examples: να3Ρα2 'good', /e92/«2 'lamb'.
Vowels have slightly lengthened allophones when occurring in a
syllable with a tone cluster: sa?2zvaz 'frog' versus sa92-3ma31 'clothing', ya2'3vi3 'hole' versus yu2-zvi3-1 'petate', so3koz 'collarbone' versus ko3'2so3 'adze'.
The vowel /e/ varies from a mid front close allophone [e] to a mid front open allophone [ε]. The close allophone occurs more frequently in couplets without a medial consonant (ve3e2 'heavy'), whereas the open allophone occurs more frequently when contiguous to a glottal stop (ve2?e2 'house').
The vowel /μ/ has a voiced bilabial syllabic nasal as an allophone which is most frequent when contiguous to /*>/: 'five'.
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 279 9. DISTRIBUTION OF PHONEMES
All couplet-initial consonant clusters begin with /s/ (alternating with /§/ when preceding /n/). Specifically: /st, s0, sc, sk, skw, sn (alternating with sn)/.
Most of the clusters are bimorphemic and occur with a causative verb. For example: stasia1 'to cure (someone)', s0il~3ei2 'to filter', sci19i3 'to grind', skq19q3 'to interpret', skwa}-ci2 'to break (it) into pieces', sna1 Vcßjsna1?α3 'to teach'.
There are a few monomorphemic nouns beginning with /st/: sta3al 'tortilla', stuZ9a3 'cobweb', scq3q3 'morning'.
All couplet-medial consonant clusters begin with /Ύ, and the second consonant is always voiced. The clusters are /7m, 7n, 9n, *?d, Ή, *?v/: nw?3ma3 'smoke', ka91nu2 'big', sa^nu1 'your (sing, fam.) boundary', sa93du3 'heel', la?2la2 'mucus', donyo2 'spring of water', ea^vi3'1 'chewing gum'. The clusters /*>b, % 9g, ?gw, / do not occur.
Prenasalized stops do not occur medial in a couplet, and voiced oral consonants are rare in that environment: άϊ3νϊ3Λ 'egg', ti3du2'3yuz-1
'a type of squash', v/1/«1 'cat', lulrul 'burro'.
When in a couplet-initial environment, some prenasalized stops are
monomorphemic (du2'3ci3'bean', za?lnu2 'old person', ga32a3 'town of Putla', jaxax 'blue') and some are bimorphemic (zq3"2?y2 'smoked', du3tu31 'whistled').
A labialized stop /kw/ may occur either initial in a couplet, or medial in a couplet: k^nu1 'swelling', si3kwi2 'milk'. A labialized stop does not, however, occur twice in the same couplet. See § 10.3, Rule 5.
In monomorphemic couplets, a rounded vowel jo, <?, u, y/ does not follow a labial consonant /kw, b, gw, v, m/. A rounded vowel may follow jmj or f\j, however, in a bimorphemic couplet: sa?2~3mu3-1 'your (sing, fam.) clothing', sfi^vu1 'your (sing, fam.) name', .si^vo1 'our (excl. fam.) name'.
Nasal vowels occur only in couplets with contiguous vowels or in a couplet whose vowels are separated by /*?/: kwq1q3 'yellow', eq39y.3 'fifteen'. In compounds, however, they may precede consonants other
than /9/: sy.z-ltu2tuz 'paper money'.
The vowel /ς/ occurs only in couplets with contiguous vowels. In a
monomorphemic couplet, /?/ occurs only next to another /ς/: t^q2 'is perspiring'. In bimorphemic couplets /ς/ may occur next to /μ/: ίξ3^1 'you (sing, fam.) are perspiring'.
Except for the two stems fe92/«2 'lamb' and skeHa2 'is running quickly',
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼280 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
in our data /e/ occurs only in a stem with contiguous vowels or with a medial /?/:je2el 'thick', te3<>e3 'vine'.
In monomorphemic couplets, nasal vowels do not follow voiced consonants. In bimorphemic couplets, however, they may follow voiced consonants: d\3-2i2 'grasped' (ti2i2 'is grasping'), zq3'2^2 'smoked' (eq19y2 'is smoking').
Most monomorphemic couplets with a medial glottal stop have a sequence of like vowels: ya2?a1 'chile', do3?o2 'adobe', ti31?i2 'rat'. In a few monomorphemic couplets, however, one vowel is low central, and the other high front or back: stu3?a3 'cobweb', Ja39i3 'mud', s[l?q2 'chickenhawk', eq^u3 'fifteen'. In bimorphemic couplets, sequences of diverse vowels separated by /?/ are frequent: sp^y31 'your (sing, fam.) leg', ve2P«1 'your (sing, fam.) house', da2^u1 'your (sing, fam.) hand', yo29ul 'your (sing, fam.) rope', da2?/1 'her (fam.) hand', yo29!1 'her (fam.) rope', sp^q3'1 'her (fam.) leg', 'our (excl.) forked limb', sci19o31 'we (excl.) are grinding'.
Most monomorphemic couplets with contiguous vowels have a se- quence of like vowels; but there are a few with diverse vowels: ei3ol 'griddle', kwi3a3 'year', stula2 'is knocking down', sa32i3 'phlegm'.
Examples of bimorphemic couplets with contiguous diverse vowels: sa3i31 'her (fam.) bird', do3il 'her (fam.) sugarcane', nu3il 'her (fam.) face' (there is no /ei/); nfia1 'her (fam.) blood' (there is no /ea/, /oa/, /ua/); v/2"3o31 'we (excl.) are pretty', ?i3Q31 'our (excl.) salt' (there is no /eo/, /ao/, /uo/); cjt1^1 'your (sing, fam.) fingernail', tq3y.1 'you (sing, fam.) are perspiring', ska1u31 'you (sing, fam.) are going up'; i/o3«1 'your (sing, fam.) sugarcane'. The vowel /e/ does not occur second in bimorphemic diverse clusters.
10. STEM PLUS PRONOMINAL SUFFIX
Some person markers have both fused and nonfused forms. Other person markers have only nonfused forms.
10.1 The first person singular familiar person marker. A stem plus the fused first person singular familiar person marker, {3}, has the same segmental phonemes as a stem without a person marker. The difference between the two forms is a difference in tone.
(1) When the stem-final syllable has tone 2 (and if the preceding syllable has tone 1 or 2, or the cluster 3-1), then the final syllable of the fused stem plus first person singular familiar has tone 3: le^lu2 'lamb',
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 281
le^lu3 'my lamb'; to9Xlo2 'rooster', ίο9ΧΙο3 'my rooster'; va3X?a2 'bad', va3X?a3 Ί am bad', lu2u2 'small', lu2uz Ί am small'.
(2) When the stem-final syllable has tone 2 (and if the preceding syllable has tone 3 or the cluster 1-3), the final syllable of the fused stem and the first person singular familiar has the cluster 2-3: sez?e2 'son', seZ9e2Z
'my son'; eix-zni2 'is intoxicated', 0ΐχ-ζηΐ2ζ Ί am intoxicated'.
(3) When the stem-final syllable has tone 1 or the cluster 3-1, the final syllable of the fused stem and first person singular familiar has the cluster 1-3: nuzux 'face', nu3uxz 'my face'; yo2<>ol 'rope', yo2?oxz 'my rope';
tazta31 'medicine', taztaxz 'my medicine'.
(4) When the stem-final syllable has tone 3, it is homophonous with
the stem plus the first person singular familiar person marker: si2siz 'aunt' or 'my aunt', tixvi3 'is blowing' or Ί am blowing'.
10.2 The second person singular familiar person marker, {-ku1}, is added to a stem as follows: (1) If the second syllable of the stem has /u1/ or Iu3"1/» or if the medial consonant is /kw/, then the nonfused -ku1 must be used: yu2?ul 'mouth', yu29ux-kux 'your mouth', vixlux 'cat', vixlux-kux 'your cat', eaztuz x 'box', eaztuz x-kux 'your box', si3kwa3X 'eyelid', si3kwa3x~kux 'your eyelid'.
(2) When the stem has a medial /?/ and diverse vowels, the second of which is /i/ or /[/, then the first syllable of the fused stem and the second person singular familiar becomes /yu/ or /nu/: da19/3 'is crying', dal?yu3x 'you are crying'; sqx?p 'boundary', sqx9nux 'your boundary'.
(3) For all other stems, the second vowel is replaced by /u/ or /y/ (if the stem has nasal vowels, the fused person marker is also nasal): ka2ni2 'is hitting', ka2nux 'you are hitting'; ne2?e2 'is scratching', ne29ux 'you are scratching'; saxta2 'dove', saxtux 'your dove'; kaza2 'bell', ka3ux 'your bell'; koxlox 'male turkey', koxlux 'your male turkey'; le^lu2 'lamb', le92lux 'your lamb'; 0izo2 'griddle', ei3ux 'your griddle'; tqx?q2 'a relative', tql?ux 'your relative'; dozox 'sugarcane', do3ux 'your sugarcane'.
(4) If the stem has the tone sequence 3 2, or if the second syllable has tone 3 or cluster 3-1, then the fused stem and second person singular familiar has -uz x or -ij31: saz0iz 'nephew', sa3mz~x 'your nephew'; vaZ9a2 'good', va39w3 1 'you are good'; do?3yo2 'spring of water', do?3yu3 x 'your spring of water'; ni2i3 'ear of corn', ni2uz x 'your ear of corn'; ka3ci3 X 'cotton', ka3cu3 x 'your cotton'.
(5) If the second syllable of the stem is tone 2 (if not part of the sequence 3 2) or tone 1, then the fused stem and second person singular
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼282 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
familiar has -u1 or -y1: to91lo2 'rooster', to?llul 'your rooster'; ve29e2 'house', ve23«1 'your house'; 0α3Λα2 'new', ^a3-1«1 'you are young'; duxcal 'goat', dulcux 'your goat'.
10.3 The third person singular feminine familiar person marker, {-i1}, is added to the stem as follows: (1) When, in the stem, /i/ contiguously follows a nonglottal consonant, then /a/ is added to form the third person singular feminine familiar: fco1«/1 'female turkey', koxniax 'her female turkey'; tu13ei3Λ 'to have pain', tul-3eia31 'she has pain'.
(2) When the stem has a medial /?/ and diverse vowels, the second of which is j\j or /}/, then the final syllable of the fused stem and the third person singular feminine familiar becomes /ya/ or/na/: da1 p/3 'is crying', da^ya31 'she is crying'; sq1 ?i2 'boundary', sq9lnql 'her boundary'.
(3) When both syllables of the stem have jij or j[j, either with or without a medial /?/, then the second vowel is replaced with /a/ or jqj: sci19i3 'is grinding', sci^a3'1 'she is grinding'; p/2/3 'badger', ?ί2αΆΛ
'her badger'; sp??-1 'leg', sp?q3 1 'her leg'.
(4) When both syllables of the stem have /e/ or /$/ either with, or
without, a medial /?/, then both vowels are replaced with f\j or /[/: je1 ?e2 'is looking', jil9ix 'she is looking'; ίξ3ξ2 'is perspiring', tpi1
'she is perspiring'.
(5) When the stem-final syllable has /ku/ or /ko/, then (except when
the first syllable has /u/ or /kw/) the final syllable of the fused stem and third person singular feminine person marker has /kwi/: 0a1'3ku3 'is laughing', ea1'3^31 'she is laughing'; silko2 'is selling', sfikVi1 'she is selling'; ji2ko2 'is grinding', ji2kwix 'she is grinding'. When the first syllable of the stem has /u/, then the /of or /u/ or the second syllable is replaced with /i/: difiku1 'is looking for', du2kil 'she is looking for'; suxku3 'high', sulki3-1 'she is tall'. When the first syllable of the stem has /kw/, then the /of or /u/ of the stem-final syllable is replaced by /i/: skMfiko1 'is turning (it), s k ^ k i 1 'she is turning (it)'.
(6) When the stem has a medial consonant other than /k/ or /Ύ, and the second vowel (but not the first) is /u/, then /if is added: salnu3 'cigar', ία1«!//3"1 'her cigar' (but, su^nu3'1 'shirt', su^ni3'1 'her shirt'); ecfitu3'1 'box', ιm3tui3-x 'her box' (but, sku^u1 'is decorating', skuUi1 'she is decorating'); le?2lu2 'lamb', le^lui1 'her lamb'.
(7) For all other stems, the second vowel is replaced by /i/, (or by III if the stem has nasal vowels): kollol 'male turkey', kollil 'her male turkey'; tq19q2 'a relative', tq19p· 'her relative'; yo29ol 'rope', jo2 9 /1 'her rope'; yu2?ul 'mouth', yu^i1 'her mouth'; ka3a2 'bell', ka3ix
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 283
'her bell'; nu3ul 'face', nu3il 'her face'; ty3^2 'charcoal', ty3^- 'her charcoal'; nifinu3'1 'bee', nu3ni31 'her bee'; salta2 'dove', salti1 'her dove'.
(8) If the stem has the tone sequence 3 2 or 1-3 2, or if the second syllable has tone 3 or the cluster 3-1, then the final syllable of the fused stem and third person singular feminine familiar person marker has the tone cluster 3-1: ti3ei2 'stomach', tfieia3-1 'her stomach'; sil-3vi2 'name', sfi ^via31 'her name'; sa30i3 'nephew', saHia3-1 'her nephew'; na3maz l 'soap', naPmi3-1 'her soap'; kq1 ?qz 'is speaking', Jcq1^31 'she is speaking'.
(9) If the second syllable of the stem was tone 2 (if not part of the sequence 3 2 or 1-3 2), or tone 1, then the fused stem and third person singular feminine familiar person marker has tone 1: tonlo2 'rooster', to^li1 'her rooster', ve2?e2 'house', v/2?/1 'her house'; stcPa1 'tortilla', sta3il 'her tortilla'; tilsil 'is whining', tfisia1 'she is whining'.
10.4 When the third person singular masculine familiar person marker, {i3}, fuses to the stem, the vowel changes are the same as those of the third person singular feminine familiar person marker, whereas the tone changes are the same as those for the first person singular familiar person marker: ko^ni1 'female turkey', ko^nia13 'his female turkey'; tixsix 'is whining', tfisia1-3 *he is whining'; sp?{3"1 'leg', sp9q13 'his leg'; eaHu3'1 'box', ea^iui13 'his box'; yo2?o1 'rope', yo^i1'3 'his rope'; sta3ax 'tortilla', sta3i13 'his tortilla'; si2si3 'aunt', si2sia3 'his aunt'; le?2lu2 'lamb', le92lui3 'his lamb'; tq1?q2 'a relative', tq1?i3 'his relative'; να31?α2 'bad', να3 1?i3 'he is bad'; sfiko2 'is selling', silkwi3 'he is selling'; se39e2 'son', si3?i2-3 'his son'.
10.5 The first person plural exclusive person marker {-ko1} may or may not fuse to the stem when it ends in one of the vowels /i, j, u, y/, but whether it does or does not fuse in that environment seems to be arbitrary: ku2eil 'to carve', kuPeo1 'we (excl.) are carving'; but du3ei2-kol
'we (excl.) are burying'; ki2nil 'is shooting', ki2nox 'we (excl.) are shoot- ing', but kvhtfi-ko1 'we (excl.) are wanting'; nu2u3 'town', no2o3 1 'our (excl.) town', but nifiul-ko1 'our (excl.) palm'; nu3'2^u3 'fire', ηοζ-2?ο3Λ
'our (excl.) fire', but yu^u^ko1 'our (excl.) mouths'.
When the first person plural exclusive person marker fuses to a stem
in which both vowels are /u/ or /y/ with a medial /?/, or with no medial consonant, both vowels change: lu2u2 'small', lo2ol 'we (excl.) are small'; iy31?y2 'money', sg3'1^1 'our (excl.) money'. When, however, both vowels of the stem are /i/ or j\j only the second vowel changes: w2"3/1
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼284 EUNICE V. PIKE AND THOMAS IBACH
'ear of corn', nft^o1 'our (excl.) ear of corn'; sp^p 'forked limb', sp?g3-i ' o u r (excl.) forked limb'.
When the first person plural exclusive person marker fuses to the stem, the tone changes are the same as those for the second person singular familiar; tixsix 'is whining', tilsol 'we (excl.) are whining'; kiZ9vi2 'is entering', ki^vo1 'we (excl.) are entering; kaxciz 'is saying', kalco31
'we (excl.) are saying'.
10.6 Other person markers follow the stem, but are not fused to it and do not cause the stem to change. They are: -yu3 Ί (polite)', -ni1 'you (sing, polite)', -na1 'she (polite)', -raz 'he (polite)', -ei2 'his or her (child)' -na9 'it', -yaz 'sacred', -kwel 'we (incl.)', -ko2yux 'you (pi. fam.)', -ko2yix 'they (fem. fam.)', -ko2yi3 'they (masc. fam.)', -na3 'they (unspecified)', -tu2 'wood', -tix 'animal', -ra1 'water'.
In addition, there are pronouns that are not bound to the stem, for example: kwe3me2ex-nix 'you (pi. polite)', jm3?m3 Ί (polite)'.
11. TONE SANDHI
There is one instance of tone sandhi. In all environments but one, the first syllable of the following words has tone 1: kwqxqz 'yellow', kwax?as 'red', kwixeiz 'white', kwixtiz 'short', ka?xnu2 'big'. When following a word which ends in tone 3, the first syllable of the above words may be tone 1, or it may alternate to the cluster 3-1: 9/2to3 kwq1!z-1qz 'yellow flower', tu2tuz 'red paper', jw2 3c73 k^i1'3·1^3 'white knife', W W kwi 1/3-1//8 'short comb', saHiz ka^'^nu2 'big nephew'.
Summer Institute of Linguistics
NOTE
1
We are grateful for the use of C. Henry Bradley's field notes. They were especially helpful in the beginning stages of the tone analysis.
REFERENCES
Bradley, C. Henry. 1970. A linguistic sketch of Jicaltepec Mixtec. Summer Institute of Linguistics publications in linguistics and related fields, 25. Norman, Oklahoma.
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
This dialect of Mixtec is spoken by approximately 14,500 speakers. They are located in the township of San Juan Mixtepec, about twenty miles west-northwest of Tlaxiaco, Oaxaca, Mexico. Various informants were used, but the principal one was Agustin Löpez Reyes. He is twenty years old and a native speaker of the language.
￼THE PHONOLOGY OF MIXTEPEC MIXTEC 285
Hunter, Georgia G., and Eunice V. Pike. 1969. The phonology and tone sandhi of Molinos Mixtec. Linguistics 47.24-40.
Mak, Cornelia. 1953. A comparison of two Mixtec tonemic systems. IJAL 19.85-100. —. 1958. The tonal system of a third Mixtec dialect. IJAL 24.61-70.
Overholt, Edward. 1961. The tonemic system of Guerrero Mixteco. A William C.
Townsend, ed. by Elson and Comas, 597-626. Mexico, D.F.
Pankratz, Leo, and Eunice V. Pike. 1967. Phonology and morphotonemics of Ayutla
Mixtec. IJAL 33.287-99.
Pike, Eunice V., and John H. Cowan. 1967. Huajuapan Mixtec phonology and morpho-
phonemics. Anthropological Linguistics 9.5.1-15.
Pike, Kenneth L. 1948. Tonemic perturbations in Mixtec with special emphasis on
tonomechanical subclasses. Tone Languages, 77-94. University of Michigan publications in linguistics, 4. Ann Arbor.
Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM
￼Brought to you by | Max-Planck-Gesellschaft - WIB6417 Authenticated Download Date | 11/11/16 1:19 AM

         </ab>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
