<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence Mille Nieves <date>20170724</date>
            </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="MN">Mille Nieves</persName>
               <date>2017.07.24</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="recieved">
               <persName resp="JB">Jack Bowers</persName>
               <date>2017.07.24</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspContext>
               <note/>
            </correspContext>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            Hi Jack,
            
            Glad that the pronoun tables are useful.
            
            One thing I want to say about all the combinations of the Mixtec pronouns table.  This table is just for you to know how Mixtec people use and combine the pronoun system, but you donꞌt have to identify the pronouns in your texts with all those details.  For example, "na" is used for people in general, it is used for distinguish participants, it is used sometimes for men, etc.  So you will identify your pronoun as 3.GNRL.HUM.FOR but in your writings you would explain the function.  The same is for ‑i which has a general use and for a man, animal, child...
            
            
            On 7/24/2017 5:11 AM, Jack Bowers wrote:
            Hi Mille,
            
            Thank you so much for the last documents you sent me, that is such a big help to me! It saves me a lot of work. I didn't know about the 'sphere', 'liquid', 'tree', 'deity/priest', or 'child' pronouns it's very exciting to learn about new features like this!  All these pronouns are common throughout the Mixtec land, although not all the pronouns are found in the existing Mixtec varieties.  For example, in some Mixtec varieties you wonꞌt find the pronoun for deity.
            
            So I naturally have some questions:
            (I)
            - Esférico: the form in the example is "ti" which is the same as the "animal" and for Líquido, the form in this is "ra" which is the same as the "3sg.m.form"
            
            &gt; Is the tone different on these or is there an error? Mixtec pronouns are toneless.  So the pronoun will get the last tone of the previous word (mostly verbs), except for yóó and pronouns for woman.  I put two accents on the vowels to distinguish it from yoo.  Another possibility (that I have to consult with my co‑worker and my Mixtec co‑workers) is to write the 1p.incl as "yoo" and the 2s.fam as yo. ?
            
            &gt;&gt;If both of these are correct but/and the tone is different, would these be candidates to add a tone marking in the orthography? The answer to your previous question is part of the answer to this question.  Adding a tone marking is what we would think first when we see contrast.  But context is more important than contrast.  The alphabet and the orthography are designed for the native speaker; in our case for the Mixtec people.  So when we add a tone marking in the orthography we have to make sure that it is extremely necessary.  This is because Mixtecs donꞌt pay too much attention to symbols and in some cases are very confusing for them.
            
            If we mark tone on Mixtec pronouns, every pronoun will have different tone markings throughout the text.  This will be more confusing for Mixtec people.  Also Mixtec people will know the tone on every pronoun.  That is not the problem.  What they should know or what they should distinguish is the aspect of the verb that appear before the pronoun.  Unlike other varieties of Mixtec, verbs in Mixtepec Mixtec have prefixes, except for the ones that have causative prefixes, iterative prefixes, and inchoative prefixes.  So we have decided to put an acute accent on the first vowel of every verb to represent the incompletive aspect (or imperfective); including the causative, iterative, and inchoative verbs. So we just have to spread the word.  Thatꞌs why I want to finish the revision of the orthography guide and the transition primer.  Meanwhile we can tell our Mixtec coworkers where to put the accent.  It will be necessary to prepare some drills as you requested for your language helper.  I am working on that.
            
            (II)
            Clearly the "-ti" and "-tu" in the animal and tree pronouns are from "kiti" and "yutu", are there any currently existing full words the "Esférico" and "Líquido" forms come from (or any of the others "deity" or "child")?  The pronoun ‑ti for animal as well as for spherical things come from kiti which means animal or horse.  The spherical pronoun does not refer strictly to spherical things.  It includes round things, oval things, and long things, among others.  I donꞌt know if there is a full word for "Liquido".  I suspect that words like that were something like: "raꞌa"? because in other varieties of Mixtec, "riꞌi" and "ruꞌu" are pronouns.  ? For example, I was wondering from where "na" (3.GNRL.HUM.FOR) come from. Recently I read an article on the web where someone was interviewing an old men at the mixteca, and he mentioned the things young people donꞌt use because they simply didnꞌt learn them or something like that.  I donꞌt remember the details, but this old men mentioned the word "naꞌa" as a pronoun.  I read this very recently.
            
            (III)
            The example "Ntsini yu" - 'I don't know' :
            
            &gt; Is the verb to 'not know' or is this missing a negator?<note> A rising tone means no</note>.  It is like "<seg xml:id="d1e65">
               <w xml:id="d1e67">nkuu</w>
            </seg>" ("<seg xml:id="d1e69" type="phrase">
               <w xml:id="d1e70">ma</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e72">kuu</w>
            </seg>" long version) <spanGrp type="annotations">
               <span target="#d1e67 #d1e69"
                     xml:lang="en"
                     resp="#MN"
                     type="translation">I canꞌt</span>
            </spanGrp>.<!-- JB? do you not need "yu"? -->
            &gt;&gt; Or is the negation expressed in tone and the tone is not written? The tone is not written (yet).
            
            (IV)
            Regarding the tables for the interlinear gloss text pronouns:
            
            You have the label "anfitrión" with the pronouns we have previously discussed as "demonstrative"/"emphatic" (sometimes reflexive) pronouns. In looking up the word "anfitrión" I can't find a definition that relates to the usage of that term in this context. (mostly the definitions have to with hosting)
            The term anfitrión is used here for the emphatic pronouns.  We donꞌt know if we will keep using this term.  If you want to use the term emphatic, to me thatꞌs fine.
            
            Last year I attended a discourse workshop and the director of the workshop noticed there were several mixtecanists present.  He reviewed several abbreviation lists of the mixtec grammars published by SIL and the abbreviation lists of the mixtecanists attending the workshop.  He wrote a guide just for mixtecanists. He realized that the term "emphatic" was used for every mixtecanist.  This is what he explained in the guide: "In the composite pronouns, the host word, itself quite empty of semantic content, has been glossed various ways in publications.  We suggest a vaguer gloss."  So I am using the term "ANFITRIÓN" for the purpose to text glossing only, but for the popular grammar I am writing, of course I will use "emphatic" or something else more familiar for the native speaker of Mixtec. 
            
            
            &gt;Could you give me some context as to how and why this term is being used?  If you refer to the term anfitrión (host), to be honest I donꞌt know much about this.  But it seems it is where a clitic is attached, since clitics cannot function on its own.  So in the case of the mixtec language, clitics would be attached to verbs, adjectives, prepositions (relational nouns), etc You name it. 
            
            Tatsa'vi nchu'a!
            <seg xml:id="d1e75" type="MWE">
               <w xml:id="d1e77">Tatsaꞌvi</w>
               <w xml:id="d1e79">meu</w>
            </seg>.
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
